Beitzah is your daf and we pick up at the top with
some Mishnah and actually today we switch away not just from Muktzah
concerns of Beis Shammai and Beis Hillel which have dominated and last
Mishnah we saw we weren't dealing exactly with Muktzah but other types
of issues of latitudes that we give people for Yom Tov about
restoring the shutters and so on but still in the rabbinic realm
and here we actually turn to a very important Mishnah in terms
of biblical aspects of Yom Tov and some of the parameters so
let's take a look. Beis Shammai omrim ein motzi'in lo es hakatan
velo es halulav velo es sefer torah li-reshus harabim u-Beis Hillel matirin.
So
here's a question, how much latitude do we have to carry on
Yom Tov? Most people assume that there's basically no prohibition of carrying
on Yom Tov, right, Yom Tov it's muttar to carry.
Whereas we find out in this Mishnah that according to Beis Shammai
it is not true. If you even if you're going to take
a minor out, carry out a child or carry a lulav or
carry a Sefer Torah, in all of these cases you are not
allowed to you are not allowed to carry. Why not? Because even
though presumably you're doing mitzvos at least with the lulav and the
Sefer Torah and the katan you could imagine, right, the katan could
be a case of similarly if we're in a mitzvah context could
be a case of Bris Milah which is what Rabbeinu Chananel says,
so you're doing all of these mitzvah things, nevertheless you're not allowed.
I mean what better reason is there than that except that it's
not for what purpose? What purpose is it not for which is
the explicit purpose which you're allowed to do things? It's ochel nefesh.
It's not done for food. So here Beis Shammai says carrying is
no different than anything else, you're allowed to do it for food,
you're not allowed to do it not for food. And as we'll
see in the Gemara, the Gemara makes it sound like that according
to Beis Shammai not only are you not allowed at some rabbinic
level but if you do it actually you would get lashes, it
would be a biblical violation of Yom Tov, that even things like
carrying it's just like anything else, only for the sake of food,
for something that's not food-related even mitzvah related it's not allowed. U-Beis
Hillel matirin, Beis Hillel allows it. Now Beis Hillel allows it here
for the sake of a mitzvah, what about if it's for other
purposes? Right, we know that we tend to carry on Yom Tov
and we don't for one minute stop and ask ourselves, one minute,
is there a sufficient justification to carry, is it a mitzvah purpose,
is it a food purpose? No you're carrying, it's Yom Tov, no
problem. Okay, so we're going to take a look at the Gemara
but here you have Beis Shammai that says you're not allowed at
all even for these important purposes and maybe even it would be
a malacha violation and Beis Hillel says you're allowed but even Beis
Hillel it's not clear how broad the allowance is. Let's take a
look at the Gemara. Tani tana kamei de-Rabbi Yitzchak bar Abdimi, so
a tana taught in front of Rabbi Yitzchak bar Abdimi, a tana
somebody who had memorized all of the Mishnayos and the Baraitas, so
he taught the following Baraita. Hashochet olah nedavah be-Yom Tov loke. If
somebody shechts a free-will olah, not an obligatory olah that you have
to bring on Yom Tov like an Olah Re'iyah but a just
a you know his own voluntary olah on Yom Tov you get
lashes. Now the reason it says olah is because you know you
can't eat from the olah, the olah is fully burned. It didn't
give like another example, I don't know, it didn't just say that
you you know you shecht it to go to waste because that's
not as interesting, that's like mekalkel. Here's a case where you're shechting
it for constructive purpose except it's not a purpose of eating. So
what would be the halacha if you did shechitah on Yom Tov
not for the purpose of eating? You shecht a korban which is
an olah which is going to fully be burned. And here he
says you get lashes. I don't care that it's shechitah, as long
as it's not for the purpose of eating then it's a violation
of malacha on Yom Tov and you get lashes. Yes.
What about the Olah Re'iyah?
So he said that's why it's olah nedavah, it's a free-will olah,
it's not an obligatory one that's supposed to be brought on Yom
Tov. Okay, so this is what the tana taught. Amar lei so
Rabbi Yitzchak bar Abdimi said to the tana, ta'ar lakh mani, who
told you this? Meaning who's like the who's like the source of
this teaching? Beis Shammai hi, this is a Beis Shammai teaching. Why
is it a Beis Shammai teaching? De-amri that they say, lo amrinan
mitokh she-huttra le-tzorekh huttra nami she-lo le-tzorekh. They say explicitly in our
Mishnah that we don't say just because carrying is allowed for a
purpose, a purpose of food, of eating, it should have it that
gives it a broader license, that means it's allowed under all context.
So we see in our Mishnah it's not true, that even though
carrying can be allowed for food purposes it remains forbidden for non-food
purposes. So presumably the same would be true by shechitah. Shechitah is
allowed for food purposes, not for non-food purposes and we see what
it means not allowed is biblically not allowed, if you're not doing
it for the sake of eating I don't care what malacha you're
doing, carrying, shechitah, whatever, you get lashes. That's a Beis Shammai position.
Ve-i Beis Hillel, if it's Beis Hillel, here's what we can infer
from our Mishnah, ha amri they say in our Mishnah, mitokh she-huttra
hotza'ah le-tzorekh huttra nami she-lo le-tzorekh. Since carrying was allowed for a
purpose, for the purpose of
eating, it's permitted for any purpose, you can even
do it
for
non-eating. If you can שחט shecht for the purpose of eating, you
can שחט shecht for any purpose, even if it's for the purpose
of being a קרבן korban not for the purpose of eating. So
there's understanding that the debate of בית הלל בית שמאי Beis Hillel
Beis Shammai is not limited to carrying. It was said in the
case of carrying, but is now a debate which would run through
all of the מלאכות melachos on יום טוב Yom Tov presumably. I'll
get back to that in a minute. Where בית שמאי Beis Shammai
would say the only allowance you ever have is if it's directed
towards food, and בית הלל Beis Hillel says once a מלאכה melacha
was permitted for food purposes, it has a blanket permission.
Now let's read a little bit more, but I just want to
pause for a moment on my statement blanket permission. Does that really
mean blanket permission? So in the two so far the examples that
we have seen are all מצוה mitzvah related: עולה, olah, לולב, lulav,
ספר תורה, sefer torah, and קטן katan it's reasonable to assume in
this context talking about ברית מילה, bris milah, which רבנו חננאל Rabbeinu
Chananel says altogether. Which רבנו חננאל Rabbeinu Chananel says. So one question
is going to be: is it a blanket permission or only for
certain things? Okay, but again, ask yourself, is that how we operate
when it comes to carrying? It's not how we operate by carrying,
we just assume it's totally מותר. mutar. But that's one question: for
what purpose? The other question is: for what מלאכה melacha are we
talking about? Do you mean to tell me that if you could
find a מלאכה melacha that could be used for a food purpose
then you have a blanket allowance for it? So for example there's
a תוספות Tosafot in שבת Shabbat that says there's a גמרא Gemara
in שבת Shabbat that if you make cheese, you're חייב chayav משום
בונה mishum boneh because you take like milk and it coagulates and
it turns to hard, it turns to cheese, it's sort of like
constructing something. So תוספות Tosafot says oh, so according to that, biblically
you would be allowed to build a building on יום טוב. Yom
Tov. Because since you can do בונה boneh to make cheese, מתוך
שהותרה לצורך הותרה נמי שלא לצורך, mitoch she-hutra l-tzorech hutra nami she-lo
l-tzorech,
and you can build a building really for any purpose. And תוספות
Tosafot says well okay, but maybe it's מדרבנן miderabbanan it's still אסור.
assur. So he actually suggests that biblically you could build a building
because of this principle of מתוך. mitoch. Now that's not nearly so
obvious and that will get us to the other question. Do you
apply מתוך mitoch to any מלאכה? melacha? Or is there something specific
about carrying and שחיטה shechita and the other things we're going to
talk about? So those are the two important principles here within בית
הלל. Beis Hillel. How much of a צורך tzorech do you need,
if any? Is it just a מצוה mitzvah or broader, it can
be used for anything? And number two, what category of מלאכות melachos
will we say this principle by? Two very critical questions about יום
טוב Yom Tov which I'll revisit. Right now I'm just putting them
on the table. Yes?
I always had this question whenever this concept comes up. I don't
understand legally what justifies making that leap. מתוך? mitoch?
Yeah. Okay, so we'll get to that. You're right, it's a very
good question. Where does this idea of מתוך mitoch come from? Okay,
so let's take a look a little bit in the גמרא. Gemara.
And that's also very true, like you don't quote a פסוק pasuk
or anything, you just make this argument. Okay, so let's take a
look.
So the גמרא Gemara says like this.
הכא נמי. hacha nami.
So we're going to get back to all those really important questions.
So מתקיף לה רבה. maskif lah Rabbah. So רבה Rabbah asked: מימאי
דבית שמאי ובית הלל בהא פליגי? mimai de-Beis Shammai u-Beis Hillel be-ha
paligi? Who tells you this is the debate? It's a debate about
a general idea applying to all מלאכות melachos of יום טוב Yom
Tov or whatever, possibly a wide range of מלאכות. melachos. If we
say do we say מתוך mitoch or not? Who says that's the
debate? דילמא בעירוב והוצאה לשבת ועירוב והוצאה ליום טוב קמיפלגי? dilma be-eruv
ve-hotza'ah le-Shabbat ve-eruv ve-hotza'ah le-Yom Tov kamiflegi? Maybe it's only a debate
about carrying. Maybe it's not about a general question by all מלאכות.
melachos. Maybe it's a carrying question. עירוב והוצאה, eruv ve-hotza'ah, a funny
phrase. But the way רש"י Rashi explains it means like sort of
like is there a concept of עירוב, eruv, which means is there
a concept of carrying? Is there a prohibition of carrying on שבת?
Shabbat? עירוב והוצאה לשבת. eruv ve-hotza'ah le-Shabbat. There is a concept of
carrying on שבת Shabbat and therefore the רבנן Rabbanan instituted all of
their rabbinic categories of עירוב חצירות eruv chatzeiros and so on. And
that we know is true by שבת. Shabbat. But maybe אין עירוב
והוצאה ליום טוב. ein eruv ve-hotza'ah le-Yom Tov. There's no prohibition of
carrying on יום טוב Yom Tov and therefore none of the דרבנן
derabbanan of עירוב. eruv. Again, it's funny why it throws in the
word עירוב, eruv, but the basic idea is: maybe the prohibition of
carrying only applies on שבת Shabbat and not on יום טוב. Yom
Tov. And this is not something that you could apply to שחיטה,
shechita, to making fires, to cooking. It's only a limited question of:
is there a prohibition of carrying on יום טוב? Yom Tov? And
that's the debate. קמיפלגי. kamiflegi.
מר סבר, mar savar, one holds, בית שמאי, Beis Shammai, עירוב והוצאה
לשבת ועירוב והוצאה ליום טוב, eruv ve-hotza'ah le-Shabbat ve-eruv ve-hotza'ah le-Yom Tov,
that there is a prohibition of carrying on יום טוב Yom Tov
and therefore the only thing you can carry for is אוכל נפש.
ochel nefesh. אך אשר יאכל לכל נפש, ach asher ye'achel le-chol nefesh,
only for אוכל נפש. ochel nefesh. That's בית שמאי's Beis Shammai position.
ומר סבר, u-mar savar, the other one, בית הלל Beis Hillel holds,
עירוב והוצאה לשבת, eruv ve-hotza'ah le-Shabbat, yes there's a prohibition of carrying
on שבת, Shabbat, ואין עירוב והוצאה ליום טוב, ve-ein eruv ve-hotza'ah le-Yom
Tov, but there's not a prohibition of carrying on יום טוב. Yom
Tov. Now why would I make that type of a distinction? כדיכתיב,
ke-dichtiv, like the verse says, ולא תוציאו משא מבתיכם ביום השבת, ve-lo
totzi'u masa mibateichem be-yom ha-Shabbat,
don't carry a load from your house on the שבת Shabbat day.
בשבת אין ביום טוב לא. be-shabbat in be-yom tov lo. It's only
a שבת Shabbat problem, not a יום טוב Yom Tov problem. Now
let's take a minute to first of all appreciate this. Number one,
what it's saying is that on the one hand that leads to
a blanket allowance. If בית הלל Beis Hillel would say fundamentally there's
no prohibition of carrying on יום טוב, Yom Tov, which is let's
face it how we tend to think about it. Then you could
carry for any purpose. You don't need to justify it. There's no
prohibition of carrying on יום טוב. Yom Tov. But what it also
means is you can't apply this to other areas. If you שחט
schecht a קרבן עולה, Korban Olah, you violated יום טוב. Yom Tov.
Any other מלאכה, melacha, you need the justification of אוכל נפש. ochel
nefesh. It's only by carrying. All other מלאכות melachos are, you need
a justification. Okay, so that is one point. It's a blanket allowance
by carrying, but it doesn't apply to other מלאכות. melachos. Now let's
talk for a minute about why carrying should be
different. Okay. So, if you take a look at רש"י, Rashi, תוספות
Tosafos develops this even more, but let's just start with רש"י. Rashi.
If you look about twelve lines down in the narrow lines, do
you see where רש"י Rashi says the line that starts with עירב
והוצא וכולי? Eirev vehotza v'chulei? Yeah. So he says, אף על
גב דאיכא הוצאה,
Af al
gav
de'ika hotza'ah,
how do we know you're not allowed to carry on שבת? Shabbos?
מויעבירו קול במחנה נפקא לן. Mivaya'aviru kol bamachaneh nafka lan. They learn
it from the verse where they made an announcement, we don't want
any more donations to the בית המקדש, Beis Hamikdash, and they learn
from that that don't bring your donations is where we learn don't
carry and don't bring. So even though we learned that, בירמיהו פירש
שלא נאסר אלא בשבת, Byermiyahu peireish shelo ne'esar ella Bishabbos, we learn
from the פסוק passuk in ירמיהו Yermiyahu ביום השבת. beyom haShabbos. It's
only a שבת Shabbos idea. ומשום הכי כשר, Umishum hachi kasher, that's
why it's allowed. That's by carrying, it doesn't apply by יום טוב.
Yom Tov. אבל שחיטה שהיא אב מלאכה, Aval shechitah shehi av melacha,
but שחיטה shechitah is different. שחיטה Shechitah is basically in the category
of מלאכות. melachos. ובכלל לא תעשה כל מלאכה היא, Uvechlal lo sa'aseh
kol melacha hi, and that was included in the prohibition of don't
do any work, which is applied by יום טוב Yom Tov as
well. אין לה כך אפילו לבית הלל, Ein la kach afilu l'Beis
Hillel, so even בית הלל Beis Hillel would say that you don't
have any allowance by שחיטה. shechitah. So why is carrying different? What
does he say? Not just we have a פסוק passuk in ירמיהו.
Yermiyahu. He suggests something more. Why is carrying different? שחיטה Shechitah is
in the primary category of לא תעשה כל מלאכה. lo sa'aseh kol
melacha. How about carrying? Where do we know carrying is from? From
the פסוק passuk of ויעבירו קול במחנה, vaya'aviru kol bamachaneh, right? It's
not included in מלאכה. melacha. רש"י Rashi suggests that carrying is almost
like a שבות, shvus, I don't know if a שבות, shvus, but
he suggests that carrying is not fundamentally in the פסוק passuk of
לא תעשה כל מלאכה. lo sa'aseh kol melacha. To learn that carrying
is forbidden, we needed a special פסוק, passuk, ויעבירו קול במחנה. vaya'aviru
kol bamachaneh. Fine. And we learn from ירמיהו Yermiyahu that that's a
שבת Shabbos הלכה. halacha. But fundamentally, carrying is not a מלאכה. melacha.
Now this is an idea that תוספות Tosafos says here as well
and says in the beginning of שבת Shabbos and that the ראשונים
Rishonim talk about, where they call carrying מלאכה גרועה, melacha gerua, like
a lowly מלאכה. melacha. Now what?
He says deficient. The word deficient here?
Well, yes, but let me say something conceptually about it. Now why
is that? Well, first of all at a conceptual level, carrying is
the one מלאכה melacha that's non-creative. It doesn't make something new. All
the other מלאכות melachos basically make something new. Carrying just takes an
object from point A to point B. Okay, so it's therefore it's
a מלאכה גרועה melacha gerua because that's conceptually why it's not the
same as the other מלאכות. melachos. And therefore also if you look
in the גמרא Gemara in שבת, Shabbos, you need a lot of
פסוקים psukim that they learn to explicitly tell you what the parameters
of carrying is, because really what does it matter? ד' אמות ברשות
הרבים, daled amos bireshus harabbim, this direction, that direction, it's just moving
something. So they learn a lot of details explicitly from the פסוקים
psukim as opposed to all the other מלאכות melachos where it's not
about the act as much as it is about what you created.
It doesn't matter how you create cooked food, frying, roasting, whatever, it's
all about the end result, whereas carrying is much more about the
act and it's much a different category of מלאכה, melacha, again, which
the ראשונים Rishonim call מלאכה גרועה. melacha gerua. And therefore, now that
doesn't mean that on שבת Shabbos that if you carry on שבת
Shabbos you haven't been מחלל שבת mechallel Shabbos and you're not חייב
מיתה. chayav misah. At the end of the day, by שבת Shabbos
it is included in the ל"ט מלאכות, lamed tes melachos, although you
might know that like you know if you read Jeffrey Gurock's history
in America and you might be aware, you know, there was a
period not so long ago where people were totally שומר שבת shomer
Shabbos except for carrying. You know, they would carry their keys. I
mean, they would never think of doing another מלאכה, melacha, but at
some psychological level like you didn't feel as much of a מלאכה
melacha even though הלכתית halachically it is. But nevertheless, by שבת, Shabbos,
fine, it's within ל"ט מלאכות lamed tes melachos but just barely. So
comes along יום טוב Yom Tov and what we learn is it's
really not in the primary category of מלאכה, melacha, and since it's
not in that primary category, it's by, it's only a הלכה halacha
by שבת, Shabbos, it's not a הלכה halacha by יום טוב. Yom
Tov. So that is an explanation why we would think carrying would
be sort of like totally different. Now I want to say another
thing about carrying as well, which is that in the פסוקים psukim
of ירמיהו, Yermiyahu, if you ask like why is carrying a problem?
Why is it so? You know, so if you think about it,
in the world of business, right,
transport is like central to what the world of commerce and business
is. I mean, you know, the transportation industry, the shipping industry, it's
all about getting goods from one place to another place. And if
you look at the פסוקים psukim in ירמיהו Yermiyahu where he talks
about how people weren't observing שבת Shabbos and you'd go into ירושלים
Yerushalayim and the stores would be open and they'd be carrying all
of the wheat and all of their stuff. into the marketplace so
the idea of like bringing all of your goods to the marketplace
for sale that's a major aspect of you know sort of the
business nature of שבת. Shabbos. But business is not the same as
מלאכה, Melacha, right? מלאכה Melacha is more about creating something. The world
of business transportation is huge. So what this is saying is is
that like by שבת Shabbos fine it will be included, but not
by יום טוב. Yom Tov. By יום טוב Yom Tov it's about
מלאכה. Melacha. It's also because since remember we just learned a minute
ago that actually you can go to the store and quote unquote
you know borrow something on יום טוב Yom Tov and you'll pay
for it afterwards. That actually we give a lot of allowance on
יום טוב Yom Tov for certain types of quasi-business in order because
to procure what you need to cook. So therefore like carrying, right?
Because look, why should carrying be the one thing allowed? Like if
I tell you you can do stuff related to food on יום
טוב, Yom Tov, you think about fire and you think about cooking,
you don't think about carrying. But if you think about getting the
materials that you need like getting all the stuff into your kitchen,
what's the first part of making food is going shopping. So that's
about carrying, that's about conveyance. Okay so that's why in general and
conceptually like if anybody stops to think like hey why do we
carry on יום טוב? Yom Tov? Huh about eating? So on the
one hand it is because it's about the shopping and the conveyance
and the getting of the material, and the other hand is what
we're also seeing here is it might even have a more blanket
allowance because it is the least of the מלאכות. Melachos. And therefore
by יום טוב Yom Tov by שבת Shabbos it's included, but by
יום טוב Yom Tov it's not acknowledged as a מלאכה. Melacha. And
that's the idea here that there's a blanket allowance. So this is
the idea that there's something said about carrying, not about the other
מלאכות, Melachos, but when it comes to carrying blanket allowance. Okay clear?
Alright there was a question Dov.
Yeah just an observation that if you if you think רש"י Rashi
seriously about the פסוקים Pesukim he'd say the same thing about fire
right away. Excellent.
I'm going to get to that. We will get to that as
well because we tend to think by יום טוב Yom Tov there's
no prohibition of carrying and there's no prohibition of fire. That's our
basic way of thinking about it, right? Not like you need a
היתר, Hetter, you need it to be for justified. We basically think
so we're going to get to the issue about fire in a
minute, so that's good we will get back to that. Okay so
let's take a look. Now I do want to say
let me just say I guess to answer one thing about what
Dov said a minute ago before the other Dov about where you
get this idea of מתוך Mitoch and where some of this is
coming from as well. Like this גמרא Gemara I have to tell
you at a conceptual and also practical level is like so central
to how you think about the מלאכות Melachos of יום טוב: Yom
Tov: carrying, other מלאכות, Melachos, מתוך Mitoch and so on. So I
want to say something about the מתוך Mitoch and a a very
significant point that רמב"ן Ramban makes about how you think about what
what the מלאכות Melachos are by יום טוב. Yom Tov. He says
there are two פסוקים. Pesukim. One פסוק Pasuk about how יום טוב
Yom Tov is different than שבת Shabbos says אך אשר יאכל לכל
נפש הוא לבדו יעשה לכם: Ach asher yeachel lechol nefesh hu levado
ye'aseh lachem: what can be eaten for any person that you have
an allowance to do. Okay and that's giving you an allowance basically
says the מלאכה Melacha is forbidden but you have an allowance when
you need to do it for the sake of אוכל נפש. Ochel
nefesh. And by the way the general explanation is is that by
שבת Shabbos the idea of cessation and rest and withdrawal dominates so
there's no היתר Hetter for אוכל נפש. Ochel nefesh. By יום טוב
Yom Tov the idea of חג Chag and שמחה Simcha dominate and
שמחה Simcha has a lot to do with being able to eat
and enjoy yourself and so on. So we have an allowance for
אך אשר יאכל לכל נפש. Ach asher yeachel lechol nefesh. That's only
one place in the תורה. Torah. Everywhere else where it's speaking about
יום טוב Yom Tov it does not say אך אשר יאכל לכל
נפש Ach asher yeachel lechol nefesh but it does say one extra
word. When it says don't do מלאכה Melacha by יום טוב Yom
Tov it says כל מלאכת עבודה לא תעשו: Kol meleches avodah lo
sa'asu: work of labor don't do. Okay whereas by שבת Shabbos it
says לא תעשה כל מלאכה Lo sa'aseh kol melacha and מלאכת עבודה
Meleches avodah is a qualifier. And the רמב"ן Ramban says what that
qualifier means: work that's about laborious as opposed to the type of
work that you do in order to make meals or whatever and
that's not labor you know that's a different
quality of work because the goal is to eat and because it's
more home-based and not out in the field and it's different type
of work. Now the difference between those so that's very nice how
those are two ways of saying the same thing but they're not
exactly saying the same thing because אך אשר יאכל לכל נפש Ach
asher yeachel lechol nefesh means every time I decide can I do
this act or not on יום טוב Yom Tov I have to
say one minute is this for the sake of אוכל נפש Ochel
nefesh or not? Do I have that justifier? Do I have the
היתר? Hetter? Because is it אוכל נפש? Ochel nefesh? If it's מלאכת
עבודה Meleches avodah then let's say I tell you you're allowed to
cook because that's not מלאכת עבודה. Meleches avodah. That's you know cooking
is not מלאכת עבודה. Meleches avodah. What I've basically done is I've
excluded cooking from the category of מלאכות Melachos that are forbidden. Right
מלאכת עבודה Meleches avodah says certain types of מלאכות Melachos are laborious
מלאכות Melachos and others are not in the category of laborious. So
it's not that every particular act I need to justify is it
אוכל נפש Ochel nefesh or not what I am saying is what
type of a מלאכה Melacha is it? If it's not a מלאכת
עבודה Meleches avodah it's מותר Muttar on יום טוב. Yom Tov. So
that allows for a more blanket type of an allowance. So part
of this issue of do you say מתוך Mitoch or not, right?
Or part of this issue do you need a justifier or not
might be like the question of do you focus on the verse
of... which means you need to justify any particular acts, fundamentally everything
is אסור, Assur, or do you say, no, fundamentally once it's מותר
Mutar it goes into the... it's not מלאכת עבודה Melachat avodah and
you have a very sort of wide berth of what is allowed.
Yes.
Actually, you could say that the תורה Torah itself gives you that
definition. There is one place where it doesn't say מלאכת עבודה, Melachat
avodah, where
it says כל
מלאכה לא יעשה בהם אשר יאכל לכל נפש. Kol melacha lo ye'aseh
va-hem asher ye'achel le-chol nefesh. So since it's defining what do I
mean by מלאכת עבודה, Melachat avodah, מלאכה Melacha that doesn't involve... exactly.
I meant to tie to say that. That's exactly the point that
the רמב"ן Ramban makes. It either says don't do any מלאכה Melacha
and then gives you the היתר Heter there of אשר יאכל לכל
נפש, Asher ye'achel le-chol nefesh, or it just says מלאכת עבודה. Melachat
avodah. So presumably it's saying how do I identify what's a מלאכת
עבודה? Melachat avodah? It's anything that's not for the purpose of אוכל
נפש. Ochel nefesh. Exactly. Those two are like parallel. Okay, but conceptually
they lead to different ways of thinking about what's the nature of
the allowance. So what do we have right now? We have a
possibility that בית שמאי Beis Shammai or בית הלל Beis Hillel hold
of a general idea of מתוך Mitoch that you would apply to
other מלאכות, Melachos, whether you'd apply completely across the board or not
is questionable. Let me actually also use this as a moment to
say, the גמרא Gemara only suggests מתוך Mitoch by carrying, שחטינג, shechting,
making the fire, and cooking. It never suggests מתוך Mitoch like תוספות
Tosfos about building a house because you're able to make cheese. Okay?
So even when the גמרא Gemara is saying that according to בית
הלל Beis Hillel you're saying מתוך, Mitoch, presumably it's centered on what
we would consider to be the primary מלאכות Melachos that are involved
in food, which is fire, cooking, שחטינג, shechting, I mean we don't
think of שחטינג shechting but yes, and carrying because as I said,
shopping is the first part of food production, right? Conveyance. So the
גמרא Gemara only suggests מתוך Mitoch in those מלאכות Melachos that are
fundamentally about cooking and therefore maybe fundamentally are in a different category.
Okay? So that's one idea. That בית הלל Beis Hillel holds of
מתוך Mitoch not limited to carrying, maybe you don't apply it to
all מלאכות Melachos but not limited to carrying, you could apply it
to other similar מלאכות Melachos as well. And then you might still
need a justification. It might not be a blanket allowance. Or בית
הלל Beis Hillel might hold it's only a דין Din of by
carrying. Carrying is a מלאכה גרועה, Melacha gru'ah, that is a blanket
allowance. I'm not going to... other things maybe are totally אסור Assur
if they're not done for the sake of food. So that's the
question. Let's take a look. Okay,
so the גמרא Gemara says like this. ומתיב ליה רב יוסף. U-mativ
lei Rav Yosef. So רב יוסף Rav Yosef asks on this idea
that it's just a carrying issue and it's not something that בית
הלל Beis Hillel would apply elsewhere. אלא מעתה, Ella me'ata, if that's
true that there's a complete blanket allowance by carrying, ליפלגו באבנים. Liflegu
be-avanim. Why not debate stones? אלא מדלא פליגי באבנים, Ella mi-de-lo pligi
be-avanim, since they're not debating stones, שמע מינה Shema mina בשלא לצורך
פליגי. be-she-lo le-tzorech pligi. They're debating the issue of carrying and
whether you have this idea of מתוך, Mitoch, but not whether you
have a blanket allowance of carrying. Now what does that mean, debate
stones? So רש"י, Rashi, it's a very strange רש"י. Rashi. רש"י Rashi
says, well, if בית הלל Beis Hillel held there was no prohibition
of carrying at all on יום טוב, Yom Tov, fundamentally carrying was
never said, then you know what else you'd be allowed to do
on יום טוב? Yom Tov? You'd be allowed to move stones, there
wouldn't be מוקצה. Muktzeh. Why? Because רש"י Rashi quotes a גמרא Gemara
that one of the reasons, there are many reasons given for מוקצה,
Muktzeh, one of the reasons given for מוקצה Muktzeh is is that
if we let you move objects around too much, then you're too
much handling objects, you'll come to walk out of your house with
it. That the whole prohibition of מוקצה Muktzeh is related to carrying.
So the way רש"י Rashi reads the גמרא'ס Gemara's question is, it
can't be fundamentally there's no idea of carrying on יום טוב. Yom
Tov. Because then בית הלל Beis Hillel would let you move stones,
there wouldn't be a category of מוקצה. Muktzeh. It must be that
fundamentally there's a prohibition of carrying, then it becomes allowed because of
the idea of מתוך. Mitoch. Once it became... so now it's true
that now pretty much it's allowed under all circumstances. But since conceptually
we start with an idea of carrying, therefore we can also have
a category of מוקצה. Muktzeh. That's the way רש"י Rashi reads it.
Now that's a little bit funny, to throw in מוקצה Muktzeh and
say why don't you debate stones? What's the easier read of the
גמרא? Gemara? The easier read of the גמרא Gemara is, and this
is... look, if בית הלל Beis Hillel said that in principle there
was absolutely no prohibition of carrying, then what should they allow? They
shouldn't just allow you to take out your קטן Katan and your
לולב Lulav and your ספר תורה, Sefer Torah, what should they allow
you to do if in principle there was no prohibition of
carrying? Stones. You wouldn't need any justification. If you wanted to just
carry a stone in רשות הרבים, Reshus ha-rabim, right? You shouldn't need
any justification. There's no prohibition of carrying. So the גמרא Gemara says
but they don't say that. Even בית הלל Beis Hillel has a
case which is somewhat justifiable, right? A קטן, Katan, a לולב, Lulav,
and so on. So therefore what you see from that is that
בית הלל Beis Hillel agrees there is a prohibition of carrying on
יום טוב Yom Tov and you say מתוך. Mitoch. I can do
it for cooking, I can do it for other reasons, but other
reasons still need to be justified. They still need to be legitimate
reasons. It's not like there's no prohibition. So yes, you have an
allowance for cooking, you have a blanket allowance of... water allowance as
well, but a broader allowance doesn't mean infinite, doesn't mean no restrictions,
it still needs to be justified. One minute, so that's the way
תוספות Tosafot *Tosafot* reads. Now that by the way, I need to
say something because that tends to be the understanding of what the
מסקנא *maskana* of the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* is. Not that there's no
prohibition of carrying, the assumption is and that the מסקנא *maskana* is
there is a prohibition of carrying, but בית הלל Beit Hillel, *Beit
Hillel* holds of this principle of מתוך Mitoch *mitoch*. If that's true,
do I need to justify why I'm carrying something on יום טוב
Yom Tov *Yom Tov*? According to רש"י Rashi *Rashi*, the answer is
no. According to רש"י Rashi, *Rashi*, once you say מתוך Mitoch. *mitoch*,
you're back to where you would have been at the beginning. Once
you say מתוך Mitoch *mitoch*, you can do anything. מתוך Mitoch *mitoch*
allows everything. But תוספות Tosafot, *Tosafot* says, reading the very reasonable read
of the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*, no, you need to be able to
justify it. You can't carry a stone. That's not in the מתוך
mitoch *mitoch* category. It still needs to be some type of צורך
*tzorech*. So how big of a צורך *tzorech* does it need to
be? Well, the most reasonable read would be of the משנה Mishnah
*Mishnah*, that it would need to be a מצוה mitzvah. צורך *mitzvah
tzorech*, because that's all the cases we're talking about. So if that's
really true, I can only carry on יום טוב Yom Tov. *Yom
Tov* if I'm doing a מצוה *mitzvah* for the sake of a
מצוה *mitzvah*? So look at the last line of תוספות Tosafot *Tosafot*
of הכי גרסינן *hachi garsinan*, where תוספות Tosafot *Tosafot* says like
this.
He says like
this. Three lines from the bottom of תוספות Tosafot *Tosafot*, middle of
the line, he says וכן פירש רבינו חננאל *vechen peresh Rabbeinu Chananel*.
Okay, he says like this. You know what, let's do the end
of the fourth line. He says ואיכא בהן צורך יום טוב Yom
Tov. קצת *ve-ika bahen tzorech yom tov ktzat*. It's true you don't
need, according to בית הלל Beit Hillel, *Beit Hillel*, to be for
food, but you need some צורך *tzorech* of יום טוב Yom Tov.
*Yom Tov*, כגון קטן למולו דמצוה נקראת לצורך יום טוב Yom Tov?
*kagon katan l'molo d'mitzvah nikreis le-tzorech yom tov*. A מצוה *mitzvah* would
be a צורך יום טוב Yom Tov. *tzorech yom tov*. לולב לשאת
ולהביא לצורך לקרות בו *lulav la-seis u-l-vosei l'tzorech likros bo*, וכן פירש
רבינו חננאל *vechen peresh Rabbeinu Chananel*. אבל *Aval*, he says, לאו lav?
להאי פירושא *lav l'hai perusha*, it's not that restrictive. לאו lav. דוקא
קטן למולו *Lav davka katan l'molo*. It wouldn't only be a ברית
מילה *bris milah* for a קטן *katan*. Okay, דהוא הדין שלא למולו
דשרי *d'hu hadin shelo l'molo d'shari*. Even though I wanted to just
take my kid on a walk on יום טוב Yom Tov, *Yom
Tov* and I had to carry him because he was a babe.
I wanted to go on a יום טוב Yom Tov? *Yom Tov
walk. It doesn't have to be a מצוה *mitzvah*. That's not, you
don't need that high of an allowance. גם טיול *Gam tiyul*, take
my child and carry him on a walk. דאשכח נמי *De-ashkach nami*.
Now how do you know that the מתוך mitoch. *mitoch* applies more
than מצוה *mitzvah* once you read the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* this way
that מתוך mitoch, *mitoch* is not infinite? Okay, because here's the example,
the proof is not in a different גמרא Gemara *Gemara*, but the
proof is what people do on יום טוב Yom Tov *Yom Tov*.
Just look outdoors, look what people do on יום טוב Yom Tov?
*Yom Tov*. He says דמשחקין בכדור שקורין פלוטא בלע"ז ביום טוב ברשות
הרבים *de-mesachakin be-kadur shekorein pelota be-la'az be-yom tov bi-rshut ha-rabim*. People play
basketball, soccer, go outside, look what people do on יום טוב Yom
Tov *Yom Tov*, they carry, they don't need a מצוה *mitzvah* purpose,
just to have fun on יום טוב Yom Tov *Yom Tov*, that's
enough. אף על פי דליכא לטיול *Af al pi d'leika l'tiyu*. Okay,
so therefore what תוספות Tosafot. *Tosafot* says is, it's true, it's not
like everything is allowed, you can't carry stones for no purpose, but
any type of thing that someone is about having a nice time
on יום טוב Yom Tov *Yom Tov*, that's included in the מתוך
mitoch *mitoch* category. So it would be pretty hard to find a
carrying that wouldn't be, you know, under this thing, but you know,
it could be like if you did something which was exactly against
the יום טוב Yom Tov. *Yom Tov* idea, like you know, somebody
said, like I don't know, can you like bring over that bookcase
that you were promising to give me? Can you bring it over
today? You were schlepping over the bookcase across רשות הרבים *reshut harabim*,
so you could say, you know what, that's not exactly appropriate for
יום טוב Yom Tov. *Yom Tov*. And once it's not appropriate for
יום טוב Yom Tov, *Yom Tov*, maybe it also is considered carrying.
Okay, but this is a fascinating idea that in some principled level,
okay, carrying is still אסור assur *assur* on יום טוב Yom Tov.
*Yom Tov* and you need justification. It's an easy threshold to reach,
but you need justification, and without any justification, that would be carrying
on יום טוב Yom Tov *Yom Tov* and that would be a
מלאכה melachah *melachah* on יום טוב Yom Tov *Yom Tov*. Having fun
is a
justification, exactly. But it's not that everything is justified. אבנים *Avanim* are
not justified. Schlepping your bookcase to your friend is not justified. Okay,
so again, three ideas here. רש"י Rashi *Rashi* says that, well, A,
we could say הוצאה *hotzah* was never forbidden. But even if you
say it was forbidden and then you have מתוך mitoch? *mitoch*, how
big is מתוך mitoch. *mitoch*? So רש"י Rashi *Rashi* says מתוך mitoch
*mitoch* is infinite. Anything is allowed. תוספות Tosafot *Tosafot* and רבינו חננאל
*Rabbeinu Chananel* say no, you still need to be justified. How much
do you have to justify it? רבינו חננאל *Rabbeinu Chananel* says it
has to be for צורך *tzorech* of a מצוה *mitzvah*, which is
a very hard criteria to meet. תוספות *Tosafot* says anything that's having
fun, any type of legitimate purpose, as long as it's not something
that you shouldn't be doing on יום טוב Yom Tov, *Yom Tov*.
Okay, but anything else is considered enough of a מתוך mitoch. *mitoch*
to make it allowed. Charlie?
Just this bringing up stones is ignoring the explanation of the first
משנה Mishnah *Mishnah* in the מסכת *masechta* that says that בית שמאי
Beit Shammai. *Beit Shammai* doesn't believe in מוקצה *muktzeh*.
Yeah, okay, but I'm not going to focus on רש"י Rashi *Rashi*'s
מוקצה *muktzehs*. Okay.
And then at the end we rejected that anyway.
Yeah, right, I know, I know.
What do stones have to do about carrying and not about בונה
*boneh*?
Well, it could be about בונה *boneh*, but but we're not...
In other words, they're saying
why... In other words, the גמרא Gemara, *Gemara* is saying because we're
not allowed to touch stones, it's because of carrying.
Therefore, why should מוקצה *muktzeh* be about carrying? Yeah, I don't want
to get into רש"י *Rashi*. When we discuss the later... when we
get to
the
later גמרא Gemara *Gemara*, we'll... Just that handling objects leads to building
also.
Yeah, okay, we'll talk about that later when we get to that
discussion. Okay, so let's take a look at the גמרא Gemara continues.
Okay, so this is the issue. And now the current argument is,
is it a general מתוך mitoch. approach, which A, might demand a
certain criteria to be met, criterion to be met, but B, could
apply to other things, so it would not just be about carrying,
it could apply to שחיטה Shechita like we said before, and could
and could say if you שחט shacht an עולה olah you haven't
transgressed. So now let's continue to see how this plays out. Okay,
so the גמרא Gemara says like
this. Okay, ואף רבי יוחנן סבר, Ve'af Rabbi Yochanan savar, and even
רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan holds, במתוך שהותרה לצורך הותרה נמי שלא לצורך
פליגי. be-mitoch she-hutra le-tzorech hutra nami shelo le-tzorech pligi. So that's the
debate. Not about carrying, but about a מתוך. mitoch Do we say
once you have an allowance for אוכל נפש, ochel nefesh, you have
a broader allowance as well? Now how do you know he holds
that? That it's not limited to carrying? דתני תנא קמיה דרבי יוחנן,
Detani tana kamei de-Rabbi Yochanan, because here's what a תנא tana taught
in front of רבי יוחנן. Rabbi Yochanan. המבשל גיד הנשה בחלב ביום
טוב ואכלו. Ha-mevashel gid ha-nasheh be-chalav be-Yom Tov ve-achalo. Okay, you're really
trying to see how many איסורים issurim you could be over at
once. Okay, so you cooked גיד הנשה gid ha-nasheh on יום טוב
Yom Tov, with milk and then you ate it. How many lashes
do you get? All of these are, sometimes the גמרא Gemara says
how many קרבן חטאות korban chattat you have to bring when it's
something you're חייב כרת. chayav kares. But this are things which are
not חייב כרת, chayav kares, but they're negative prohibitions, so it's how
many different sets of lashes will you get? Okay, so לוקה חמש.
lokeh chamesh. He gets five sets of lashes. לוקה משום מבשל גיד.
Lokeh mishum mevashel gid. You cooked a גיד. gid. Now there's no
prohibition to cook גיד gid except that it also happens to be
יום טוב. Yom Tov So you cooked without a legitimate purpose. Okay,
because you're not allowed to eat a גיד, gid, so the cooking
was not legitimate. So you're חייב chayav for cooking on יום טוב.
Yom Tov לוקה משום אוכל גיד. Lokeh mishum ochel gid. You're חייב
chayav for eating a גיד הנשה gid ha-nasheh even if it didn't
have milk. לוקה משום מבשל בשר בחלב. Lokeh mishum mevashel basar be-chalav.
You get lashes for cooking meat and milk together, because this assumes
a גיד gid is considered meat, which is debated. ולוקה משום אוכל
בשר בחלב. U-lokeh mishum ochel basar be-chalav. And then you ate it,
so you get lashes for eating meat and milk. ולוקה משום הבערה.
U-lokeh mishum havarah. And you get lashes because of הבערה, havarah, because
of the fire that you made. Now before we get to what
the response is, רש״י Rashi says, it's a very funny רש״י. Rashi.
רש״י Rashi says when it, about the גמרא Gemara where you get
lashes for cooking, for cooking meat and milk together, רש״י Rashi says,
רש״י Rashi says, yeah, and you know what, it's אסור assur not
only to eat meat and milk together, but even to cook it
together. How do I know it? Because it says three times לא
תבשל גדי בחלב אמו. lo tvashel gdi be-chalav imo. One to tell
you not to eat, one to tell you not to get הנאה,
hana'ah, one to tell you not to cook. So I read that
רש״י Rashi and I, I burst out laughing because it was like,
how do I know that it's אסור assur to cook meat and
milk? Because three times it says it and one of the three
times is to tell you don't cook meat and milk. Every single
time it says לא תבשל גדי בחלב אמו. lo tvashel gdi be-chalav
imo. But the funny thing is we have so internalized that the
prohibition is just about eating that רש״י Rashi has to like prove
to you that it's even forbidden to cook it. I mean, okay,
but anyway...
Can I ask,
it's got to be היתר בהיתר? heter be-heter? I don't understand why
is it בשר בחלב basar be-chalav here if this is אסור assur.
anyway?
What, what are you talking about? This גיד הנשה gid ha-nasheh is
אסור. assur You mean the problem of אין איסור חל על איסור?
ein issur chal al issur? Yeah. Okay, so that's a good question
about אין איסור חל על איסור. ein issur chal al issur. But,
but, there it could be that, you know, there are answers to
that. Like in one case is בשר בחלב basar be-chalav is also
אסור בהנאה, assur be-hana'ah, it's not just as opposed to גיד הנשה
gid ha-nasheh which isn't אסור בהנאה. assur be-hana'ah. But that's a good
question. Like why do you, why, what happened to אין איסור חל
על איסור? ein issur chal al issur? That also comes up a
lot. That's by eating, not by the cooking issue. It comes up
a lot of are you, are you חייב chayav by like in
the case of let's say, I don't know, a cheeseburger, like from
McDonald's because it's already אסור assur because of נבילה. neveilah. So it's
also אסור בהנאה assur be-hana'ah by once it's cooked...
but it would be היתר בהיתר heter be-heter right, also?
No, there's not a principle of היתר בהיתר. heter be-heter. No, no.
The paradigmatic case is היתר בהיתר. heter be-heter. It doesn't require היתר
בהיתר. heter be-heter. The only question is אין איסור חל על איסור.
ein issur chal al issur. If it's already אסור assur can it
become אסור assur again? Okay. Anyway, let's take a look. So the
גמרא Gemara. says, so now he says this. So according to that
ברייתא, braita, it sounds like we said before. Like it sounds like,
you know, if you cooked and you didn't have a good justifiable
reason, you get lashes. Okay, so that's what it sounds like. If
you cooked without a justifiable reason, you get lashes. And the same
with making a fire
on יום טוב. Yom Tov. So אמר ליה, Amar lei, רבי יוחנן
Rabbi Yochanan said to the תנא, tana, פוק תני לברא. Puk tani
le-vara. Go teach your ברייתא braita somewhere else, outside. Meaning, this, I
don't hold of this ברייתא. braita. Why? הבערה ובישול אינה משנה. Havarah
u-vishul einah mishnah.
You should not have in that making a fire and cooking, because
in the end you don't, you wouldn't get lashes for those. And
why not? ואי תימצי לומר משנה, Ve-im timtzei lomar mishnah, if you
say that it does belong in there, בית שמאי היא. Beit Shammai
hi. Then this ברייתא braita would be בית שמאי. Beit Shammai? Why
would it be בית שמאי? Beit Shammai דאמרי בית שמאי, De-amri Beit
Shammai, who say בית שמאי Beis Shammai would say, לא אמרינן מתוך
שהותרה לצורך הותרה נמי שלא לצורך. lo amrinan mitoch she-hutra le-tzorech hutra
nami shelo le-tzorech. The same way they say that you don't say
מתוך mitoch and you have broader allowance by carrying, הכא נמי לא
אמרינן מתוך שהותרה הבערה לצורך הותרה נמי שלא לצורך. hacha nami lo
amrinan mitoch she-hutra havarah le-tzorech hutra nami shelo le-tzorech. They also would
say that you don't say מתוך mitoch that because fire was permitted
for a need it was also permitted not for a need. have
a broader allowance when it comes to cooking and making a fire
and therefore they would say you get lashes. But if it'd be
בית הלל, Beit Hillel if it's בית הלל, Beit Hillel כיון דאמרי
מתוך שהותרה לצורך הותרה נמי שלא לצורך, kivan d'amri mitoch she'hutra letzorach
hutra nami she'lo letzorach, once they say that carrying you got a
broader allowance because it started with eating for eating purposes but it
became a broader allowance, הותרה לצורך הותרה נמי שלא לצורך, hutra letzorach
hutra nami she'lo letzorach, הכא נמי, hacha nami,
here too by cooking and making a fire, מתוך שהותרה לצורך הותרה
נמי שלא לצורך, mitoch she'hutra letzorach hutra nami she'lo letzorach,
you wouldn't get lashes for making a fire or cooking because you
have a broader allowance. So you see that רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan
feels that בית הלל Beis Hillel is not just about carrying. בית
הלל's Beis Hillel, idea is a broader idea of מתוך mitoch and
could be applied to cooking and making a fire. And therefore he
says you wouldn't get lashes because of the principle of מתוך. mitoch
Now somebody should be yelling at me and saying, "רבי Rabbi Linzer,
you just gave an example of a guy שלעפינג schlepping stones according
to תוספות or שלעפינג schlepping a bookcase where you wouldn't say that
that falls under the מתוך, mitoch. it's not a legitimate use." So
according to רש"י that says מתוך Mitoch allows everything, fine, everything is
allowed here as well. But if you need some justification, how is
cooking גיד הנשה בחלב gid hanashe b'chalav a justification? How does that
fall under מתוך? So take a look at תוספות, הכא נמי, hacha
nami, כיון שהותרה, kivan she'hutra, ואם תאמר מה צורך איכא במבשל גיד
כיון שאסור? ve'im tomar mah tzorech ika b'mevashel gid kivan she'asar? יש
לומר כיון שהיה בדעתו של זה לאכלו היינו צורך יום טוב. yesh
lomar kivan she'hayah beda'ato shel zeh le'achlo hayinu tzorech Yom Tov.
Since in your subjective mindset you were doing it for the sake
of eating, even though it was an אסור assur, eating, I don't
know if you had to maybe not be aware that it was
אסור, assur maybe you were, but nevertheless, maybe anything related to eating,
even an אסור assur eating, still falls under this expanded מתוך. So
we're starting to see that תוספות's מתוך is getting pretty close to
רש"י, since it also includes cooking for eating even when everything is
אסור assur to be cooked and so on. But it's not עד
הסוף. ad hasof. So let me just end this סוגיא sugya by
saying the following things. So we can tend to treat carrying as
though it's not אסור assur at all. Although we also tend to
treat something else as though it's not אסור assur at all. Not
just carrying. What else do we treat as not אסור assur at
all? Do we really
say, "do I need to justify doing this or not?" What other
מלאכה melachah do we tend to not feel we need to justify
if we're going to do on יום טוב? Yom Tov, Cooking. Cooking
and making a fire, I would say more, but you want to
transfer a fire. You don't say, "one minute, wait, wait, is there
a good justification for this?" Transferring a fire... no, making is דרבנן,
de'rabanan, but transferring a fire. Okay, we tend to feel like, "oh,
it's not אסור assur to make a fire on יום טוב." Yom
Tov. There's no איסור issur to make a fire, it's יום טוב,
Yom Tov. right? That's how we feel. Now, as we see in
the גמרא, Gemara. the only מלאכה melachah, you can say categorically was
not אסור possibly
was carrying. Whereas we don't, we say by other things like making
a fire that there's a broader allowance. So the general assumption is
that
the whole sort of thrust of this גמרא Gemara as well is
that it's about the principle of מתוך. It's not that these things
were categorically excluded. There's a principle of מתוך. מתוך applies not in
all of the ל"ט מלאכות, lamed tet melachot, like תוספות making cheese
and building buildings. We've seen מתוך in the גמרא Gemara under what
cases? Carrying, שעכטינג, shechting, fire, cooking. And those are things that are
all essential things
about making food. And that's exactly where we think we have a
pretty broad allowance. Fire, cooking, and carrying, right? So the question that
remains in the פוסקים Poskim is do you need any justification? And
I'll give you an example, for example, the ירושלמי Yerushalmi asks a
question of נר של בטלה. ner shel battalah. Can you light a
candle for no purpose on יום טוב? Yom Tov. Is that allowed?
Do you need some justification? And I'll give you an example where
this comes up, you'll be surprised a little, but the פוסקים Poskim
say, "how about lighting candles
on יום טוב after it's already יום טוב? Because now why is
that a problem? Well, let's face it, we have electric lights. You
don't really need the candle. Oh, but you're doing it, it's a
מנהג, minhag, it's a מצוה." Okay, well how about, this is what
they ask, how about if you're making הבדלה Havdalah between
שבת Shabbat going into יום טוב and you make a נר ner
and the idea of having two flames like a, as opposed to
a single flame is really just a מנהג, minhag, it's not an
עיקר הלכה. ikkar halachah. So are you really allowed to light both
flames because it's really not technically needed? And they say, "oh,
but it's a מנהג," minhag, that's enough of a justification. But do
you need any justification or is it completely blanket allowed? How broad
does מתוך go? So psychologically we think מתוך allows everything, but there's
an interesting lingering question of do you need some degree of justification?
And I want to end by saying the point that תוספות said,
which is that maybe the reason we tend to focus on carrying
and fire is the same way carrying is singled out as not
a real מלאכה, melachah. fire on the one hand can be a
paradigmatic מלאכה. melachah What's a bigger מלאכה melacha than fire? Like the
whole way we end שבת, Shabbat, fire's all about creativity and so...
But fire is also the one, another case of a מלאכה that's
mentioned in the תורה, Torah, לא תבערו אש בכל משבתיכם ביום השבת.
Lo teva'aru esh bechol moshvoteichem beyom ha-Shabbos. And there's an opinion in
the גמרא Gemara that making a fire is not one of the
ל"ט מלאכות lamed tes melachos and you're not חייב מיתה, chayav misa,
הבערה ללאו יצאת. havara le-lav yatzas.
So it is interesting that the two cases which we think we
have an almost, you know, pretty much like a categorical allowance might
be that they're at the edges of the ל"ט מלאכות. lamed tes
melachos. But the real way the גמרא Gemara seems to conceptualize it
is this principle of מתוך and it's left as a question of
how broad is מתוך. Do you need any justification for doing things?
But again, the level of justification is very, very low, so it's
almost always possible to reach.
Remind us from the לשון lashon of the תורה Torah how you
know it's something is כרת kares or a לאו?
Well, every time it says לא lo it's a לאו. And כרת
kares or חייב מיתה, chayav misa, so by שבת Shabbos it's מחלליה
מות יומת, mechalleleiha mos yumas, so that puts
it... That's explicitly. Yeah. Yeah, you don't infer כרת. kares. Okay. So
now we go on to, so that as I said was like
such a central סוגיא sugya conceptually and practically about
how יום טוב is different than שבת Shabbos and at which what
allowances you have and what מלאכות melachos are allowed.
But isn't it true that even with everything you've just said, nothing
is as radical as this little תוספות. In other words, it's in
his mind. Like if it's in your mind it's a שמחה simcha
for you. Right.
Well, רש"י is more radical. רש"י basically says you don't need to
justify it at all.
Even in your mind.
Yeah. מתוך means there's no need to justify it anymore. But תוספות
you need to justify it, but almost anything will qualify as legitimate
justification. Right. Now it could be because it's about eating, right, and
the eating is what makes it, is what gives it that היתר
heter idea. Okay, anyway. Now we get back to דרבננס, derabbununs, okay?
Just so funny how we shift gears. בית שמאי אומרים, אין מוליכין
חלה ומתנות לכהן ביום טוב. Beis Shammai omrim ein molichin challah u-matanos
le-Kohen be-Yom Tov You
cannot deliver חלה challah or hand even if the כהן Kohen shows
up at your door, חלה challah or the gift, the gifts is
when you שחט shacht an animal, you give the זרוע לחיים וקיבה,
zero'a lechayayim ve-keivah, right, the the arm and the cheek and the
maw, you give it to, you give it to a כהן. Kohen.
Okay. Now, the point is you're allowed to on יום טוב שחט.
shacht. We've been talking about that. You're allowed to make fresh bread,
that was the דף daf that Charlie did, and once we're allowing
you to make fresh bread, what do you have to do in
order to eat the bread? You have to separate חלה. challah. So
we allow you to take חלה. challah. If we're allowing you to
שחט, shacht, we allow you to separate off the מתנות. matanos. Not
like you, it's not like the animal is טרף treif before you
separate off the מתנות, matanos, but practically, you don't want to start
eating without setting them aside or else they'll get mixed up and
you'll come to steal from the כהן. Kohen. So we allow you
to make fresh bread and to שחט shacht and we allow you
to separate off the חלה, challah, separate off the מתנות. matanos. Do
we allow you to now give those to the כהן? Kohen? Okay.
Maybe that you'll have to wait until after יום טוב. And let's,
and the reason that we should not want you to do it,
as we're going to see in the גמרא Gemara is, because if
you start giving the כהן Kohen the gift, then you'll come to
give the כהן Kohen the most common gift, which is תרומה. terumah.
And תרומה terumah you're not allowed to separate on יום טוב. So
it's all like don't give the כהן Kohen חלה challah and מתנות
matanos even though you separated them off, because you'll come to give
him תרומה, terumah, as you come to give him תרומה terumah you'll
come to separate תרומה. terumah. So it seems like a big גזירה
לגזירה, gezeira le-gezeira, but that's the issue. Okay. בית שמאי אומרים Beis
Shammai omrim, אין מוליכין חלה ומתנות לכהן ביום טוב ein molichin challah
u-matanos le-Kohen be-Yom Tov. בין שהורמו מאמש bein she-hurmu me-emesh whether you
separated off the חלה challah and the gifts the night before, before
it was יום טוב, בין שהורמו מהיום bein she-hurmu me-hayom whether they
were separated on יום טוב. And you might think that if you
did it on יום טוב and you had an allowance to do
it on יום טוב and you couldn't have done it last night
because you only made the חלה challah today, maybe once you were
allowed to do it and you had no other option, you're allowed
to give it to the כהן. Kohen. No. Can't give it to
the כהן Kohen under either circumstances. ובית הלל מתירים. u-Veis Hillel mattirin.
בית הלל Beis Hillel allows presumably under both circumstances. Either if you
did it today where you had no other choice and maybe even
if you separated it off yesterday, you're still allowed to deliver it
to the כהן Kohen today. אמרו להם בית שמאי, Amru lahem Beis
Shammai, בית שמאי Beis Shammai said to בית הלל, Beis Hillel גזירה
שוה. gezeira shava. Look, let's make an analogy. Now גזירה שוה gezeira
shava normally means a technical way of linking a similar word in
one verse to another and learning out הלכות. halachos. But scholars have
said, רש"י says this is a derivative use of the word גזירה
שוה gezeira shava which just means let's compare the two cases. But
scholars have said the opposite. This is the original use of גזירה
שוה. gezeira shava. גזירה שוה gezeira shava started by saying look let's
compare, let's, you know, let's compare the two cases. And once it
became an issue of let's, you know, let's line the two cases
up and compare them, it became later to be used to mean
just the technical existence of the same word in the same in
different verses allows you to learn הלכות. halachos. But here it's not
even about verses, it's about two דרבננס. derabbununs. But גזירה שוה gezeira
shava says let's compare them, גזירה שוה gezeira shava let's make, let's
compare the two cases. חלה ומתנות מתנה לכהן, challah u-matanos matana le-Kohen,
so
the חלה challah and the gifts from the animal are a gift
to the כהן. Kohen. ותרומה מתנה לכהן ve-terumah matana le-Kohen and the
תרומה terumah is a gift to the כהן. Kohen. כשם שאין מוליכין
את התרומה כך אין מוליכין את המתנות. keshem she-ein molichin es ha-terumah
kach ein molichin es ha-matanos. The same way
you'll concede
that you can't deliver תרומה terumah to the כהן Kohen even if
it were separated before יום טוב, you can't deliver these gifts to
the כהן. Kohen. אמרו להם בית הלל. Amru lahem Beis Hillel. בית
הלל Beis Hillel. said that's לא, lo, not true. אם אמרתם בתרומה
שאינו זכאי im amartem bi-trumah she-eino zakai But תאמר במתנות, tomar b'matanos,
these things you're allowed to separate them on יום טוב, חלה challah
and the
and the gifts of the animal, and therefore if you're allowed to
separate them we're also going to allow you to give them. A,
it's just completing the process and B, if is even if giving
even if it leads to separating, separating isn't the problem. Let's take
a look at the גמרא. Gemara קסלקא דעתך, kasalka dach’tach, we're assuming
כשהורמו מהיום ושנשחטו מהיום וכשהורמו מאמש ושנשחטו מאמש, keshehuremu mehayom u’shenishchetu mehayom
u’keshehuremu me’emesh u’shenishchetu me’emesh,
when בית שמאי Beis Shammai when the משנה Mishnah says whether it
was from yesterday or today
it means whether it was, you know, שחט-ed shecht today and separated
today or שחט-ed shecht yesterday and separated yesterday. We'll see as we
continue why it will matter. The basic point being that if it
was שחט-ed shecht today it's more of a reason to allow it
because or if the bread was baked today because you had no
opportunity to do it before as opposed to a scenario where the
bread was baked yesterday or the animal was שחט-ed shecht yesterday but
you only separated it off today. Then at least if you were
more on top of things you could have taken care of all
of this yesterday. Okay but we're assuming that the משנה Mishnah. is
talking about even if everything was done today, בית שמאי Beis Shammai
still says that it's forbidden. Let's take a look. מאני מתניתין? mani
masnisin? לא רבי יוסי ולא רבי יהודה lo Reb Yossi v’lo Reb
Yehuda אלא אחרים. ela acherim. Who
is our משנה Mishnah. going by? Not רבי יוסי Reb Yossi and
not רבי יהודה Reb Yehuda but others. What does that mean? So
now we're going to quote a ברייתא braisa that says three different
versions of this debate of בית שמאי Beis Shammai and בית הלל
Beis Hillel and we're going to try to figure out which one
corresponds to our משנה. Mishnah דתניא, datanya, taught a ברייתא. braisa. אמר
רבי יהודה, amar Reb Yehuda, says רבי יהודה, Reb Yehuda, לא נחלקו
בית שמאי ובית הלל על מתנות שהורמו מערב יום טוב lo necheliku
Beis Shammai u’Beis Hillel al matanos shehuremu me’erev Yom Tov שמוליכין עם
המתנות שהורמו מהיום ושנשחטו מהיום. shemolichin im hamatanos shehuremu mehayom u’shenishchetu mehayom.
So here's what he says: if you actually שחט-ed shecht the animal
today or baked the bread today, everybody agrees since you had no
choice, no opportunity to do it yesterday, everybody agrees you could deliver
it today. Not only does בית שמאי Beis Shammai say you could
deliver it today if you שחט-ed shecht it today, but once you're
delivering this bread and these gifts you can bundle in with it
stuff that had been waiting from yesterday. Okay? So that actually בית
שמאי Beis Shammai will allow you those cases, to bundle it together
and starting with the stuff that was done today that's okay. Okay,
that everybody agrees
to. לא נחלקו אלא להוליכן בפני עצמן. lo necheliku ela leholichan bifnei
atzman. The only issue is yesterday's stuff and to do it by
themselves. שבית שמאי אומרים אין מוליכין ובית הלל אומרים מוליכין, sheBeis Shammai
omrim ein molichin u’Beis Hillel omrim molichin, that you can't do by
themselves. וכך היו בית שמאי דנין, v’kach hayu Beis Shammai danin, and
this was what בית שמאי Beis Shammai would say to בית הלל.
Beis Hillel חלה ומתנות מתנה לכהן ותרומה מתנה לכהן. challah u’matanos matanah
l’kohen u’trumah matanah l’kohen. Look, the חלה challah and the gifts are
a gift and the תרומה trumah is a gift. So כשם שאין
מוליכין את התרומה, keshem she’ein molichin es hatrumah, the same
way you can't take תרומה, trumah, כך אין מוליכין את המתנות, kach
ein molichin es hamatanos, you can't give these give them by itself.
אמרו להם בית הלל, amru lahem Beis Hillel, בית הלל Beis Hillel
said no. לא, אם אמרתם בתרומה שאינו זכאי בהרמתה, lo, im amartem
bitrumah she’eino zakai b’haramasah, תרומה trumah you can't give by itself because
you have no allowance to take תרומה. trumah. תאמר במתנות שזכאי בהרמתן,
tomar b’matanos shezakai b’haramasan, these
you're allowed to take on יום טוב and therefore even though you
could have done it before יום טוב you can still deliver it
on יום טוב. Okay so according to them, what we get is
that בית שמאי Beis Shammai concedes you can deliver the stuff that
was שחט-ed shecht today and he even concedes that you can bundle
it together. That's one version. Okay that's רבי יהודה. Reb Yehuda. אמר
רבי יוסי, amar Reb Yossi, says רבי יוסי, Reb Yossi, לא נחלקו
בית שמאי ובית הלל על המתנות שמוליכין. lo necheliku Beis Shammai u’Beis
Hillel al hamatanos shemolichin. בית הלל Beis Hillel and בית שמאי Beis
Shammai agree that you can deliver the gift. Even the stuff presumably
that was from before יום טוב, even בית שמאי Beis Shammai will
let you do that. לא נחלקו אלא על התרומה. lo necheliku ela
al hatrumah. What they're debating is whether you can even give
תרומה. trumah. That בית שמאי Beis Shammai agrees you can give all
this stuff, the question is can you even give תרומה trumah and
even that בית הלל Beis Hillel will
allow. Okay? So לא נחלקו אלא על התרומה. lo necheliku ela al
hatrumah. שבית שמאי אומרים אין מוליכין, sheBeis Shammai omrim ein molichin, you
can't give תרומה trumah for obvious reasons, meaning deliver
it, ובית הלל אומרים מוליכין, u’Beis Hillel omrim molichin, you can. וכך
היו בית הלל דנין, v’kach hayu Beis Hillel danin, and it was
בית הלל Beis Hillel that made the comparison. Now that you everybody
concedes these other gifts, they're going to try to argue on the
strength of that to תרומה. trumah. חלה ומתנות מתנה לכהן ותרומה מתנה
לכהן. challah u’matanos matanah l’kohen u’trumah matanah l’kohen. The you know these
are all gifts to the כהן. kohen. כשם שמוליכין את המתנות, keshem
shemolichin es hamatanos, the same way you בית שמאי Beis Shammai concede
that you
can give the חלה challah and the parts of the animal, כך
מוליכין את התרומה, kach molichin es hatrumah, you should concede that you
can give תרומה. trumah. אמרו להם בית שמאי, amru lahem Beis Shammai,
בית שמאי Beis Shammai said back, לא, lo, I don't no it's
not a good
comparison. אם אמרתם במתנות שזכאי בהרמתן, im amartem b’matanos shezakai b’haramasan, by
the other things you can give to the כהן kohen because you're
allowed to separate them. תאמר בתרומה שאינו זכאי בהרמתה, tomar bitrumah she’eino
zakai b’haramasah, but this תרומה trumah you cannot give. So according to
this version we they're only debating תרומה. trumah. Now clearly this version
is not the author of our משנה. Mishnah, Our משנה Mishnah has
everybody agrees you cannot give תרומה trumah and they're debating the other
stuff.
But בית הלל Beis Hillel according to that would say you could
even separate out? No, no, they've already been taken and then you
can give it.
It's only about it's only about handing it over, it's not about
delivering it. אחרים אומרים, acherim omrim, others say, לא נחלקו בית שמאי
ובית הלל על תרומה שאין מוליכין, lo necheliku Beis Shammai u’Beis Hillel
al trumah she’ein molichin, okay, which is what we've been assuming, everybody
agrees you can't give תרומה. trumah. ולא נחלקו אלא על מתנות. v’lo
necheliku ela al matanos.
and they debate the gifts, שבית שמאי אומרים, sheBeis Shammai omrim, בית
שמאי Beis Shammai says, אין מוליכין, ein molichin, you cannot deliver them,
ובית הלל אומרים מוליכין, u'Beis Hillel omrim molichin, you can deliver them.
Now, that's how that's different than the first position, because the first
position had בית שמאי Beis Shammai saying you could bundle them up,
okay, and also the first position had בית שמאי Beis Shammai conceding
that you can give gifts that were shechted today if the animal
was shechted today or the bread was baked today. This sounds like
בית שמאי Beis Shammai doesn't concede anything. Okay, so the question is
which one is our משנה, Mishnah the first one or the last
one? So since in our משנה Mishnah it sounds like בית שמאי
Beis Shammai says I don't care whether it was yesterday or today,
it sounds like our משנה Mishnah is אחרים, Acherim, that בית שמאי
Beis Shammai doesn't concede anything. So let's take a look at the
גמרא. So לימא, leima, so the גמרא says like this: So לימא
אחרים היא ולא רבי יהודה? leima Acherim hi velo Reb Yehuda? It
sounds like our משנה Mishnah. is אחרים Acherim because according—that בית שמאי
Beis Shammai doesn't concede anything and not רבי יהודה Reb Yehuda that
has בית שמאי Beis Shammai conceding in the case when it was
shechted today or baked today. So אמר רבא, amar Rava, says רבא:
Rava: No, מי קתני mi-ktani our משנה Mishnah doesn't say
שהורמו מהיום ושנשחטו מהיום? shehurmu mehayom ve-shenish-chetu mehayom? Doesn't say we're talking
about a case when it was shechted today or baked today. שהורמו
קתני. Shehurmu ktani. It says we're talking about a case when it
was separated today. That's where בית שמאי Beis Shammai doesn't
concede. ולעולם שחיטתן מאמש. Ule'olam shechitatan me'emesh. But the case would be
where it was shechted yesterday, so that could be the case of
our משנה. Mishnah Our משנה Mishnah, might have בית שמאי Beis Shammai
not conceding because we're not talking about shechted today or baked today,
it was shechted or baked yesterday, it was separated today or yesterday.
Maybe it was separated today but shechted yesterday. But it could be
according to our משנה Mishnah that בית שמאי Beis Shammai would say
that if it is shechted today, it is allowed, and that's the
position of רבי יהודה. Reb Yehuda. Okay, so the גמרא says
so
where are we? ולעולם שחיטתן מאמש. Ule'olam shechitatan me'emesh. So לימא רבי
יהודה היא ולא אחרים? leima Reb Yehuda hi velo Acherim? Okay, if
that's the case of the משנה, that it was shechted yesterday and
therefore בית שמאי Beis Shammai would concede if it was shechted today
that it's okay, then maybe we'll say the
opposite. Our משנה is just רבי יהודה, Reb Yehuda, not אחרים. Acherim.
No, אפילו תימא אחרים. afilu teima Acherim. Even the אחרים, Acherim, the
last position, could say that בית שמאי Beis Shammai would concede when
it was shechted today. ובהנך דנשחטו מאמש, Uve'hanach denishchetu me'emesh, even the
last position would say that בית שמאי Beis Shammai only argues when
it was shechted yesterday. Shechted today בית שמאי Beis Shammai would agree.
So now we're saying that the last position, when it says בית
שמאי Beis Shammai doesn't concede, would still say they concede when it
was shechted today. So that's just like רבי יהודה, Reb Yehuda, who
says בית שמאי Beis Shammai would concede when it was shechted today.
What's the difference? So the גמרא says אי הכי היינו רבי יהודה?
i hachi, haynu Reb Yehuda? Isn't that now you're saying the same
thing as רבי יהודה? Reb Yehuda? No, איכא בינייהו טפילה. ika beinayhu
tfeila. The debate would be this idea of making it secondary, of
bundling it up. Okay, so everybody might say that בית שמאי Beis
Shammai agrees if it was shechted today it's okay, where רבי יהודה
Reb Yehuda goes one step further to say that they would not
only say that's okay, they would even say that once you're giving
the
stuff that was shechted today, you can bundle up with it the
stuff that, you know, was shechted already yesterday. Okay, so what we've
basically said is, it's not clear what cases בית שמאי Beis Shammai
concedes, but the גמרא is moving—maybe nothing, maybe everything except תרומה. trumah.
גמרא is moving to this position that maybe בית שמאי Beis Shammai
will concede about things that are freshly baked today and shechted today,
argued just when it was done yesterday. Let's take a look at
one more line of the גמרא to get some sense of closure.
אמר רב יהודה אמר שמואל הלכה כרבי יוסי. Amar Rav Yehuda amar
Shmuel halacha k'Rebbi Yosi. Bet you weren't expecting that. We rule like
רבי יוסי Rebbi Yosi who says that everybody agrees that all of
the מתנות matanos are okay and the only debate is about the
תרומה. trumah. So that according to this, according to בית הלל Beis
Hillel you could even deliver תרומה trumah on יום טוב. You just
can't separate it. And let's read one
case. טובי בריה דרב נחמיה, Tuvi breih d'Rav Nechemiah, so טובי Tuvi
the son of רב נחמיה, Rav Nechemiah, הוה ליה גרבא דחמרא דתרומה,
hava lei garva dechamra d'trumah, he had like a flask of wine
which was תרומה trumah and he wanted to give it to the
כהן. kohen. It was a יום טוב. He had separated it before
and he wanted to give it today. אתא לקמיה דרבי יוסי, Ata
lekamei d'Reb Yosi, he came before רבי יוסי. Reb Yosi. אמר ליה,
Amar lei, מהו לאמטויי לכהן האידנא? mahu l'amtuyei l'kohen ha'idna? Could I
give this to the כהן kohen today? It's stuff I had laying
over in my house, you know, it's from a week before, but
can I give it to the כהן kohen today? אמר ליה, Amar
lei, he said to him: הכי אמר רב יהודה אמר שמואל הלכה
כרבי יוסי. hachi amar Rav Yehuda amar Shmuel halacha k'Rebbi Yosi. Yes,
we rule like רבי יוסי. Rebbi Yosi. Go ahead, give it to
the כהן kohen today. בית הלל and בית שמאי both agree you
can give מתנות. matanos. They're only debating תרומה. trumah. And even though
you can't separate תרומה, trumah, we wind up ruling like בית הלל
that you can deliver תרומה trumah on יום טוב. Okay.